Finding Aid for Office of Ethics and Religion (University of Michigan) records 1860-1991
Bentley Historical Library, University of Michigan
- Student Religious Association 1936-1956, 6 linear feet
  - Topical
    - Conference, National Conference of College Chaplains 1949 (Box 8)
    - Conference on the Cell Group 1947 (Box 8)
    - Conference on the Cell Group 1948 (Box 8)
    - Conference on Religious Journalism 1946 (Box 8)
    - Conference on the Unification of Religious Work in the University of Michigan (Box 8)
    - Conference Planning 1953 (Box 8)
    - Conference, Social Action 1947 (Box 8)
    - Conference, Youth Retreat 1945 (Box 8)
    - Constitution and By-Laws (Box 8)
    - Day of Prayer 1938-1943 (Box 8)
    - Departmental Project reports (Box 8)
    - Discussion Groups (Box 8)
    - Displaced Persons Committee (Box 8)
    - Faculty Conference (Box 8)
    - Fireside sessions 1938-1939 (Box 8)
    - Foreign Student Speakers/International Banquets (Box 8)
    - Forums (Box 8)
    - Freshmen 1938-1944 (Box 8)
    - Graduate Student Luncheon Group (Box 8)
    - Hazen Foundation (Box 8)
    - Heifers for Europe (Box 8)
    - Human Relations Workshop 1954 (Box 8)
    - Insight (Student Magazine) 1945-1947 (Box 8)
    - Institute on Cultural Conflict (Box 8)
    - Intercultural Outings (Box 8)
    - Inter-Faith Symposium (Box 8)
    - Jewish Student Problems (Box 8)
    - Leadership Retreat 1947 (Box 8)
    - Leadership Retreat 1949 (Box 8)
    - Leadership Retreat 1950 (Box 8)
    - Library, Books, etc. (Box 8)
    - Marriage Relations Course (Box 8)
    - Membership Lists 1940-1943 (Box 8)
    - Michigan Student Christian Vocation (Box 8)
    - Military Units (Box 8)
    - Morning Watch 1937-1938 (Box 8)
    - Music Seminar 1944 (Box 8)
    - Music Seminar and Carol Sing (Box 8)
    - Nation and World Committee (Box 8)
    - National Youth Administration 1937-1943 (Box 8)
    - Office of the President (Box 8)
    - Office of Student Affairs (Box 8)
    - Personnel 1939-1944 (Box 8)
    - Personnel Director 1944 (Box 8)
    - Professional Religious Work Students (Box 8)
    - Programs 1939-1943 (Box 8)
    - Protestant Consultant to Students from Other Lands (Box 8)
    - Preaching Mission (Box 8)
    - Radio Program (Box 8)
    - Reconciliation Trips (Box 8)
    - Relief Drive (Box 8)
    - Religion in Life 1950-1952, 3 folders (Box 8)
    - Research Consultant on Religious Education-E.W. Blakeman (Box 9)
    - Retreats (Box 9)
    - Retreat Planning 1952-1953 (Box 9)
    - Round Table (Box 9)
    - Seminar, Art (Box 9)
    - Seminar, Bible (Box 9)
    - Seminar on Comparative Religions 1946 (Box 9)
    - Seminar, Oriental Religions (Box 9)
    - Seminar-Sociology of Religion (Box 9)
    - Seminar, Theology (Box 9)
    - Social Service Work (Box 9)
    - State Student Christian Conference (Box 9)
    - Student Town Hall (Box 9)
    - Theology Forum (Box 9)
    - United Peace Committee (Box 9)
    - United Student Christian Council (Box 9)
    - University Choir 1938 (Box 9)
    - Vesper Services (Box 9)
    - Veterans' Organization (Box 9)
    - WHRV Radio Broadcasts 1948 (Box 9)
    - Willow Village Program (Box 9)
    - Work Camps (Box 9)
    - Workshop for Understanding Between the Faiths 1946 (Box 9)
    - World Students' Christian Federation (Box 9)
    - World Student Service Fund 1940-1948, 5 folders (Box 9)
    - Worship Services (Box 9)
    - Y.M.C.A (Box 9)
    - Mimeographed flyers and mailings 1937-1948, 4 folders (Box 9)
  - Related Organizations
    - Inter-Guild
      (succeeded by the University Christian Federation, Inter-Guild started out as SRA committee but later became semi-independent agency)
      - Minutes and other papers 1937-1955, 6 folders (Box 9)
      - Conferences 1939-1943 (Box 9)
      - Constitution, etc (Box 9)
      - Michigan Student Christian Consultation (Box 9)
      - Miscellaneous (Box 9)
      - News Bulletins (Box 9)
      - Retreats 1947-1953 (Box 9)
    - Campus Religious Council 1945-1954 (Box 9)
      (succeeded by the Association of Religious Counselors)
    - Christian Student Directors Association minute book 1944-1955 (Box 9)
  - Scrapbooks
    - 1944-1949 (Box 10)
    - 1949 (Box 10)
    - 1950-1951 (Box 10)
    - 1953-1954 (Box 10)
- Visual Materials
  - Photographs
    The Photographs are mainly from the period of the Student Religious Association (1937-1955) with a scattering of photos from the period of SCA.
    - Album 1936 of photographs of participants and activities of the Freshman Rendezvous Camp (Box 10)
    - Photographs of retreat at Fresh Air Camp 1950s (Box 10)
    - Lake Geneva conferences 1920s (Box 10)
    - Miscellaneous, 2 folders (Box 10)
- Office of Religious Affairs 1955-1968, 1 linear feet
  The office of religious Affairs subgroup (1955-1968; 1 linear foot) consists of two series, Topical Files and Related Organizations. Within the latter series are notebooks of records documenting the activities of the Association of Religious Counselors, the Christian Federation Advisors, and the Board of Directors of Religious Affairs.
  In 1993, additional records were received from the Office of Ethics and Religion. Spanning the years 1912-1991 (bulk, 1965-1991), this accession includes records relating to predecessor organizations as well as the Office of Ethics and Religion. The records are divided into four series: Topical Files, Program Files, University Values Year, and Printed Works.
  - Topical Files 1956-1966
    - All-Campus Conference on Religion 1956 (Box 11)
    - All-Campus Conference on Religion 1957 (Box 11)
    - All-University Counseling Study Committee 1957 (Box 11)
    - Alumni and Commencement Breakfast 1961 (Box 11)
    - Centennial Celebration 1958 (Box 11)
    - Commission on Curriculum 1963-1964 (Box 11)
    - Committee on Studies in Religion (Box 11)
    - Conference, Martin Buber 1957 (Box 11)
    - Conference on Vocations in Religion (Seminary Days) 1963 (Box 11)
    - Curriculum (Box 11)
    - Ecumenical Ministry (Box 11)
    - Freshman Rendezvous 1957-1963, 2 folders (Box 11)
    - Human Relations Workshop 1958 (Box 11)
    - Lane Hall (Box 11)
    - Organization/establishment (Box 11)
    - Programs 1958-1963 (Box 11)
    - Purpose and function (Box 11)
    - Student Counseling Services (Box 11)
    - Student Government Council (Box 11)
    - Workshop in Religious Counseling 1958 (Box 11)
    - Workshop in Religious Counseling, Financing (Box 11)
    - Workshop on Religions 1957-1958 (Box 11)
    - Writer in Residence, Louis Lomax 1966 (Box 11)
  - Related Organizations
    - Board of Governors of Religious Affairs (Box 12)
      - Record books 1955-1964, 2 volumes (Box 12)
    - Association of Religious Counselors
      - Record books 1956-1968, 2 volumes (Box 12)
    - Christian Federation Advisors (name changed in 1962 to Ecumenical Campus Staff)
      - Record books 1955-1964, 2 volumes (Box 12)
  - Scrapbook 1958-1959
    - 1958-1959 (Box 13)
  - Printed Material
    The Printed Works series (.3 linear feet) contains annual reports spanning the years 1949-1982. Also included are two newsletters entitled Circuit and Interim, and miscellaneous bulletins and pamphlets. This series has been combined with printed works received prior to 1993.
    - Printed material (Box 14)
      (not further described)
  - Topical Files 1962-1985
    The Topical Files (.8 linear feet) are composed of an alphabetical run of working files. The researcher will find the files sketchy, but indicative of the kinds of religious activities on the University of Michigan campus. Particularly well documented are the files of the University Interfaith Center, a corporation formed by the Association of Religious counselors in 1963. The files document the unsuccessful attempt to construct a religious facility on the north campus of the University of Michigan, which would have provided worship services, religious education, and counseling. Related information on this topic can be found within the "Association of Religious Counselors" files. For a complete summary of the activities of the OER on an annual basis, the researcher should consult the "Annual Reports" in Printed Works (box 14).
    - Association of Religious Counselors
      - General 1962-1970 (Box 15)
      - Minutes 1961-1971 (Box 15)
        (1964-1968 missing)
      - North Campus Development Committee 1966 (Box 15)
    - Black Religious Experience (seminar) undated (Box 15)
    - Commission on the Role and Function of Religious Groups on Campus 1965 (Box 15)
    - Completing the Circle 1984-1992 (Box 15)
      (Black student enrichment event)
    - Ethics and the University Project 1974 (Box 15)
    - Historical Materials 1912-1977 (Box 15)
    - Last Lecture (lecture series) 1976-1977 (Box 15)
    - Latin American Lecture Series 1972 (Box 15)
    - Male/Female Relationship Workshop 1975-1983 (Box 15)
    - Paper, 1970: Value Trends and Religious Trends at University of Michigan (Box 15)
    - Political Correctness Conference 1991 (Box 15)
    - Programs 1966-1978 (listing) (Box 15)
    - Religious Census (U of M campus) 1919-1975 (Box 15)
    - Report, 1974: A Survey of Student Religious Needs: A Review of the Ongoing Work in the Office of Ethics and Religion (Box 15)
    - Student Christian Association 1948 (history) (Box 15)
    - Student Religious Organizations Survey undated (Box 15)
    - Teaching Ethics and Values, Conference on 1988 (Box 15)
    - University Christian Federation 1956-1957 (Box 15)
    - University Council on Religious Affairs (minutes) 1975 (Box 15)
    - University of Michigan Interfaith Center
      - General 1966-1971 (Box 15)
      - Board of Trustees (minutes) 1965-1971 (Box 15)
      - Board of Trustees Roster 1967-1970 (Box 15)
      - Building Campaign 1967-1970 (Box 15)
    - University Planning Committee on Religion in the University 1972-1976 (Box 15)
    - Vietnam Conference 1965 (Box 15)
    - Women and Religion 1975-1980 (Box 15)
    - Women 1970-1971 (Box 15)
  - Program Files 1965-1992, 0.9 linear feet
    The Program Files (.9 linear feet) are arranged chronologically by academic year. The files are a very rich source on the programs sponsored or co-sponsored by the Office of Ethics and Religion. These programs, which facilitated awareness of religious and ethical issues included lectures, conferences, workshops, and movies. The researcher will find fliers, brochures, and memoranda describing the various speakers and events. Themes include world hunger, human rights, U.S. policy in foreign affairs, concerns of women and minorities, and religions of the world.
    - Undated (Box 15)
    - 1965-1972 (Box 15)
    - 1975-1976 (Box 15)
    - 1976-1977 (Box 15)
    - 1977-1978 (Box 16)
    - 1978-1979 (Box 16)
    - 1979-1980 (Box 16)
    - 1981-1982 (Box 16)
    - 1982-1983 (Box 16)
    - 1983-1984 (Box 16)
    - 1984-1985 (Box 16)
    - 1985-1986 (Box 16)
    - 1986-1987 (Box 16)
    - 1987-1988 (Box 16)
    - 1988-1989 (Box 16)
    - 1989-1990 (Box 16)
    - 1990-1991 (Box 16)
    - 1991-1992 (Box 16)
  - University Values Year 1973-1980, 0.6 linear feet
    The University Values Year series (.6 linear feet). contains information regarding the two-year cooperative venture that was concerned with the ethical dimensions of university life. Funded by President Robben Fleming, proposed by the University Council on Religious Affairs, and administered by the OER, this university-wide program was concerned with educating students about the ethical issues arising from scholarly life and practice. Through these files, the researcher can trace the program from "Imparting Values," a speech delivered by Robben Fleming (General, 1973-1974) to the several evaluative reports of the program.
    - General
      - 1973-1974 (Box 16)
      - 1975-1977 (Box 16)
    - Conferences (miscellaneous) 1976 (Box 16)
    - Coordinating Committee (minutes) 1975-1976 (Box 16)
    - Decentralization and the Values of Authority and Autonomy 1976 (Box 16)
    - Grants in Aid
      - Correspondence 1974-1975 (Box 16)
      - Proposals 1974-1975 (Box 16)
    - Institute of Public Policy Studies 1976 (Box 16)
    - Library Values Seminar 1976 (Box 16)
    - Medicines, Use of 1976 (Box 16)
    - Narcissism in Modern Society (conference) 1977 (Box 16)
    - Peace and Conflict Studies Program 1976 (Box 17)
    - Program on Human Issues and Values 1976 (Box 17)
    - Religion 1976-1980 (Box 17)
    - Report of the Coordinating Committee
      - 1974-1975 (Box 17)
      - 1975-1976 (Box 17)
    - Reports
      - Cotman undated (Box 17)
        (evaluation of university values program)
      - Cotman, Background Materials 1975-1976 (Box 17)
      - Asking Questions in a Large State University: A Case Study, 1978 (Box 17)
      - Decentralization and the Values of Authority and Autonomy: A Study of Reciprocal Effects, circa 1977 (Box 17)
      - Report of the Coordinating Committee on the 1974-1975 Values Year and Futures Proposal, 1975 (Box 17)
      - Report of the Coordinating Committee on the 1975-1976 Values Program, 1976 (Box 17)
      - Report on the University Values Program, undated (Box 17)
    - Seminar on Values and Decision Making 1976 (final report) (Box 17)
    - Seminar Survey 1975 (Box 17)
    - Social Learnings: Issues and Methodologies of Values Education 1976 (course proposal) (Box 17)
    - Study of University Future 1975 (Box 17)
    - Weekly Seminar 1974-1975 (Box 17)
    - Working Drafts 1975 (Box 17)
Related Material
For additional information on the Office of Ethics and Religion at the University of Michigan, the researcher should consult the records of the University of Michigan. Vice President for Student Affairs.
The researcher should also consult the Bentley Historical Library's printed works catalog under the heading "University of Michigan - Office of Ethics and Religion" for descriptions of other printed materials.